and one more Anna
Anna this is looking extremely clean
here's one issue though
we've been training all this time and
I've allowed
your footwork to develop naturally and
I've instructed you on some
technical things regarding the feet but
we never really went in depth and
there's been some bad habits that have
developed unfortunately
bad habit number one is that you stand
in place a lot we talked about this last
time you're not on your toes
and also
some of your footwork fundamentals are
wrong so in today's lesson I'm going to
teach you
how to keep positioning yourself between
the shots and we're going to go over
some footwork fundamentals okay and are
you ready for this yes are you sure okay
let's do this the first thing we're
going to do is called hot feet okay you
heard about this
okay so basically you're gonna go like
this you're gonna stay on your toes and
keep your heels off the ground for 30
seconds okay I did this with a lot of my
juniors and it's called hot feet
increase the intensity a little bit
there you go come on you keep going
there you go come on keep going
and seriously this is very similar to
dance come a little closer Come a Little
Closer you're backing away from me like
this okay rack it up like this ready
position
and hot feet come on
can we got 10 more seconds Anna
there you go
come on keep the heels up
and take a break
you see what I'm saying you're going to
take 15 second break and we'll do it
again I wish we did it
before and I did this a lot I've said it
to you a gazillion times keep your feet
moving you know stay on your toes but
we're gonna have to go to the extreme
and do hot feet now
I didn't think I would have to pull out
this exercise but I have to and do it
again go hot feet
come on come on come on come on come on
goanna go
go and I go
and good enough nice work all right go
here in a ready position
and I want you to do hot feet now prior
to hitting the ball go ahead do hot feet
hot feet
hot feet and forehand
there you go do it again hot feet
and backhand
again hot feeds
and forehand Anna come
okay hot feet again
come on keep going hot feet and forehand
then I do big steps to it well you're
doing good there you moved well yes now
Anna answer me honestly how annoying is
it to do hot feet on a scale on a scale
from one to ten really annoying
experience I have to tell you it reminds
me of a butt shake and Latin dancing
what is it called Latin dancing butt
shake butt shake yes oh yeah and it's
literally
this that's a technical term and dance
butt shake
is it okay do the butt shake okay we
don't call it hot feet we call it butt
cheeks
all right you gotta do the butt shake
between the shots okay that way
I told you but I use different
terminology I think when I say butt
shake it's gonna click a little bit more
but in other words what's going to
happen when you do the butt shake you're
gonna be able to position yourself and
get yourself in a better position on
a lot of these shots where you're
committing too early and setting too
early and now you're at the mercy of the
incoming ball yeah so what I always have
told you to move as long as possible and
not to set too early so what I'm telling
you now you know different words is to
shake your butt as long as possible
and then I uh I can have bigger steps to
the I can have bigger steps to the
position or this is a like phenomenal
question it doesn't have to be an exact
science because you're not going to be
able to look down on your feet and see
exactly how you're moving nice
nice thank you so much all right no
these are a little bit older these are
the Rafa shoes is Rafa on the back
and uh now I'm gonna reveal my one of my
biggest secrets I throw my shoes in the
washing machine okay and it cleans and
they come out like new
okay but I lost my train of thought now
what was I saying before remind me see
my brain is fried
too much computer
too many too many tick tocks yeah but I
don't I'm losing my memory
you think it's going to be a reversible
damage yes
Anna I got it again okay you're not able
to look down on your feet and know how
they're moving exactly
so you're gonna have to go by feel in
other words you don't have to count the
steps or make specific movements just go
by feel but what it should feel like is
you being on your toes and continuing to
move gotcha and the key is the purpose
of doing this is so that you're in a
good position that's what you have to
understand
now in the whole context of how you're
going to move he has to make sense in
the stroke that you're hitting so this
is another lesson that we had a long
time ago where the sequence the
movements have to be sequenced correctly
okay so remember there's a three-part
sequence right
right this actually the second video I
ever released on YouTube I talk about
the three-part sequence and the sequence
number one is already positioned and now
the what's it called again the butt
shake the butcher can be part of the
ready position so you don't have to be
like this you can go like this and
you're ready position now you see your
forehand the first thing you're going to
do is you're going to turn towards the
forehand side and now you're going to
set up and you're going to find the ball
in the setup phase and while you're
finding the ball that might require a
little bit more of that
footwork adjustments because you don't
know exactly what's going to happen to
the ball so you might have to adjust a
little bit more and then finally when
you feel like you're in a good position
that's when you set and you hit and it
happens actually inside the stroke okay
so in your mind you have to set up
forever
and keep your feet moving it's going to
feel really awkward it's going to feel
really unnatural
a lot of people are more comfortable
just standing and playing but your
improvement is going to be limited when
you do that in order to progress to the
next levels you will have to improve
your footwork yeah okay so let's go over
it again here's the ready position we're
going to move we're going to see your
forehand we're going to turn set up
set and hit like this okay all right
let's do this all right so ready
position do the hot feet
turn go
okay so there was a mistake there yes a
fundamental mistake where you went like
this and the forehand came and you went
like this to the floor you moved
laterally so remember the three-part
sequence you're in a ready position you
see it's a forehand what do you do first
you turn towards the forehand side now
your movements are not lateral anymore
now they're going to be forward
okay and then you set up to the ball
and go come
Anna this is so crisp come
it's okay come again ready
go
so there's another fundamental mistake
that you're doing and that is the
following so you're hitting a forehead
from here let's say for example right go
ahead and stand here
and so what you do now instead of
moving laterally to the middle you turn
your entire body around and you go like
this
okay now what happens if the person hits
it back to this side now you have to
turn back around and go this way so it's
not
a good way to move we've covered this a
while back in a lesson I remember that
we talked about this so the way you have
to move back to the middle is in a
lateral way so you can change directions
faster
okay so you're going to hit a forehand
from here you're going to move laterally
this way
ready position then you go through the
same sequence come here
hit laterally back to the Middle with
side steps
and then you go through the whole
process again now there's one exception
to the rule let's say that you're more
in an emergency situation over here and
way off the court
and you leave the entire court open now
moving laterally to the other side would
take too long so in that case you would
turn around and run back that way okay
okay so there are exceptions to the rule
but generally speaking you always want
to move back to the middle laterally
does that make sense yes all right let's
try it again
angle
laterally yeah Santa comp
much better footwork lateral and again
comp
Anna you're looking like a pro now
here we go come
and this is maybe some of the best
movement I've ever seen from you get up
to it
a little bit of a frame it's okay again
ready come on ready stay on your toes
and go come
laterally back to the middle match point
right here
one more time back to the middle it's
all right come again ready
up
now how do you move back when so how do
you move back to the middle when you
like say for example closer you take the
shortest distance back to the middle
okay a lot of people take detours so a
lot of people will play a ball from here
and now they'll go back here this way
yeah yeah and then they'll go to the
middle okay okay it's a detour okay so
you always want the quickest way back to
the middle so you hit a forehand from
here
you go back to the middle this way and
you always want to keep your eyes on the
other side don't ever turn around and go
back like this not that you were doing
this but some people make this mistake
okay but always have in your mind that
you want to come back to the middle of
the Court got it all right here we go
again come
maybe the cleanest forehand you hit by
so now here comes the real test we're
going to play back and forth and you're
going to try to do some of the same
things okay come on
good Anna
better
up up
yes
better
don't turn your body like this come on
face me more
good
footwork
Come on Feet moving
don't get stationary come up
good back to The Middle come on back to
the middle here's what you have to
remind yourself in that sequence of
movements
the reaction time is is very important
so when you see it's a forehand with
lightning speed you turn yourself
towards that side and there has to also
be a Readiness to do so so you can't
just be like this you won't react as
fast so the Readiness is going to allow
you to react faster in an athletic
position a wide base
and now you see your forehand you go
right here you see that oh I see your
forehand there it is and now I set up
you see the quick feet there look again
I see it's going to be a forehand and I
go like right there
huh I I think I do that
actually
I am consciously aware of doing that
but here's a still choked but the
mistake in your movement is often that
in that first step you're still sideways
when you do here so what I'm asking you
to do is something more specific and
that is this right here you see this
yeah yeah so you see your forehand you
turn yourself yeah and it's going to be
a quicker way of getting to the ball
then going like this and then turning
somewhere in there
you understand so it has to make sense
in the context of what's Happening we're
playing with each other you see it's a
forehand you right away go pop right
here and then you set up and when you're
done you have to make a
effort to recover the right way you're
still recovering the old way you're
going like you're hitting here and
you're going like this you're hitting a
ball from here
and you're going like this you're not
you're yeah you're not you're not
building the correct
muscle memory for the fundamentally
correct footwork yeah that's
that's done but think about it if you
play and you hit a forehand
and you go does this make any sense to
go like this you won't be able to see
what's happening over there yeah all
right so you have to really watch what's
happening on the other side all right
let's do it again come on
okay see that one was a little that was
a nice shot but there was a little bit
slower the movement you went like this
and then like this
instead of going right away this
better
good Anna
again don't stop moving Anna come on
keep your feet moving turn
that was probably the best one you hit
so far okay it's getting there
and I'm good
and I clean try try come
okay even though you missed it I like
the way you reacted to that ball I
remember even when the ball is in front
of you you still go through the same
sequence you turn here and then you run
forward so you run forward the body
slightly turn towards the side
yes
would work
good
good try try
Anna what happened there's another thing
that we have to work on which I call
stationary footwork that's where a lot
of Rec players get into trouble when
they're in the middle of the Court
and they're rallying with someone
they're hitting right at each other they
just stand there
they associate the fact the ball is
coming right to them with not having to
move at all and that's a mistake yeah
because every ball intent is
unpredictable even one that comes right
at you you don't know exactly how it's
going to balance how it's going to come
at you so now I would like to work on
stationary footwork meaning I'm going to
be right in the middle or the other side
at the net we're going to go back and
forth to each other I'm going to be
directing the ball right at you
but despite that I want you to stay away
from the temptation to just stand there
with the heels touching the ground I
want you to do the exact same sequencing
that we practiced before on your toes
hot feet set up the shot all the
progressions that we did before we're
gonna do them now but the ball is going
to be coming right at you okay all right
let's do it right here anna come on we
got this
come on come on come on
better
late
come in I keep moving
good and do you see the difficulty of
like even balls that are coming right at
you how much movement it requires how
much intensity yeah before commitment
it's very deceiving because you're you
know balls coming right to the middle
you think oh I could just stand there
and play but you can't
there was a lot better the way you moved
today we have to continue along this
path and follow some of these footwork
fundamentals you're doing good Anna
nice work